<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-08-21T14:20:00+08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Nakata – An Appreciation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/secret-footballer/nakata-an-appreciation.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/secret-footballer/nakata-an-appreciation.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-21T14:20:00+08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-08-21T14:57:11+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I could feel that the team were playing just for money and not for the sake of having fun. I always felt that a team was like a big family, but it stopped being like that. I was sad, that’s why I stopped at only 29.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Hidetoshi Nakata&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many of us, playing professional football is the dream. Hidetoshi Nakata was not only lucky enough to live it, he managed to reach the very top of the game is widely seen as a trailblazer for Asians to ply their trade in Europe. The 2002 World Cup jointly hosted by South Korea and Japan brought the Asian game to a whole new level and demonstrated just how important a market it was for European club football to recruit legitimate talent that paid for itself commercially. On the back of it, Lee Young-pyo and Park Ji-sung were two other Asian players that earned moves to Europe after the tournament. Players from Japan, South Korea, Iran and other Asian regions are regular features in leagues all over Europe today, but no Asian player could come close to what Nakata had to offer. Yasuhiko Okudera may have been the first Asian to score in the European Cup while Cha Bum-kun may have been the first Asian to win a European trophy, but their brilliance was unfortunate to be on show in an era where commercialism had yet to take over the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that sense, Nakata was the perfect specimen. A huge star in Asia, his model good looks combined with his undoubted playing ability made him the ultimate package for clubs – able to deliver both on the pitch and off it. His bright performances at the 1998 World Cup made several clubs in Europe sit up and take notice, with Perugia eventually beating out several clubs to secure his signature. Critics were quick to dismiss his chances. How could the boy inspired by Captain Tsubasa make his mark in arguably the best league in the world? Comic book fantasy is one thing but cutting it in the real world was another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paying no heed to his doubters, Nakata promptly scored two goals on his debut against the reigning champions, Juventus. Perugia may have lost 4-3, but the Nakata effect was lost on no one. He would go on to score 10 league goals that season, the highest tally of his career. Over 5,000 Japanese fans turned up to see his debut in Serie A, stunning Italian officials. When Japanese travel agencies began offering one-day trips to Umbria to catch Nakata in action for Perugia, the average Japanese attendance at matches was about 3,000 – no small matter for a club whose stadium capacity was only 28,000. The replica Nakata 7 shirt was also a bestseller in Japan, with close to 70,000 being ordered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time, Nakata’s unparalleled commercial potential was fully recognised. In addition to his marketability for any club that employed him, Nakata’s ability to spot a pass, beat a man and make late runs into the area did not go unnoticed. Amid reports of bids from Manchester United and interest from Monaco, Nakata eventually moved to Roma as Francesco Totti’s understudy for the not so tiny sum of €21m – the most expensive fee ever paid for an Asian footballer. In Rome, he enhanced his reputation further as a classy attacking midfielder, making his own impact on Italian football despite not being a regular starter for the first team. The highlight of his club career came in a crunch match against Juventus, who were Roma’s main rivals for the Scudetto in 2001. Coming on for Totti, Nakata set about imposing himself, passing the ball around and stamping his authority on the game. With Roma trailing 2-0, Nakata unleashed a 25-yard screamer past a helpless Edwin van der Sar to get Roma back into the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/OFMH5tJP9wU?start=18" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a goal that stunned the Delle Alpi and millions worldwide as they played witness to a rare sight – a Fabio Capello smile. With a minute remaining, Nakata powered another shot towards goal which van der Sar could only parry, allowing Vincenzo Montella to scramble the ball in for the equaliser. Roma had maintained their advantage at the top of the table, a lead they would not relinquish for the rest of the season. It was to be the only league title of Nakata’s career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, Nakata was undoubtedly Asia’s best and most well-known player. Parma came calling with a bid of €28m and Roma decided to cash in on the Japanese superstar. Perhaps attracted by the opportunity of first-team football, Nakata left the reigning Italian champions, and went on to make 76 appearances in his first two seasons with Parma, winning the Coppa Italia in 2002 – the last trophy of his career. It was at this point that his form took a serious downturn. All of a sudden, he could no longer influence games and was dispossessed far too easily. Rumours of his private life were a constant topic in tabloids while fans suspecting he was far more interested in fashion and other endeavours than his career. During the season, Parma were also declared bankrupt after the owner, Calisto Tanzi, was found to have embezzled money from his Parmalat company which also went out of business. Nakata would be shipped off to Bologna, but by now, his passion was long gone, with the embers of his career fading by the day. He would change clubs three times in as many years, moving from Bologna, to Fiorentina, before winding up his career in rainy Lancashire with Bolton Wanderers. He would only score three goals in the last three years of his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of Japan’s 2006 World Cup campaign, Nakata announced his retirement to the shock of the football world, especially in his native Japan. He was Asia’s best player and should have been the prime of his career at 29 years of age. But the love for the game had died a long time ago. Subsequent interviews in later years would reveal how he no longer wanted to play football as it turned into a job, as opposed to the passion he once had. But at the heart of it all was a desire to learn more about the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All my life, I played just football. I didn't know what the world was like outside of football,” he told CNN in an interview earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since his retirement, Nakata has travelled extensively to various parts of the world, using his fame to cultivate awareness as well as to drive his philanthropic endeavours. He launched his charitable foundation, Take Action, in 2008, which organised charity matches in Japan and abroad. While on his travels, people he met would ask him about Japan and Nakata quickly discovered that he did not know much about his homeland. This prompted a self-discovery tour of his country, where he would soak up the culture and knowledge as he visited all 47 prefectures. He launched his own brand of sake as a way to preserve a key part of Japan’s tradition, having first become enamoured with wine cellars during his playing career in Italy. Nakata aims to make Japanese culture more accessible to the West, placing a high emphasis on tradition in an age where the Internet is king. Already accustomed to playing an unofficial ambassadorial role wherever he goes, few would bet against him doing just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all his extracurricular interests, Nakata will always be remembered for his role and contribution to Asian football, proving to clubs that Asian talents are more than just marketing tools. Where people only expected him to penetrate markets, he also penetrated opposition defences with his menacing runs and incisive passing. And for that, Asia has much to thank him for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I think football is the best tool to communicate with other people, to connect the people. It's beyond the countries, it's beyond languages. Football is the biggest thing to share, to connect the entire world so … even outside the stadium, I can play football to connect the people.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Hidetoshi Nakata&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Sunday Afternoon Kickabout with Mountview Rangers FC</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/asian-league-review/a-sunday-afternoon-kickabout-with-mountview-rangers-fc.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/asian-league-review/a-sunday-afternoon-kickabout-with-mountview-rangers-fc.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-19T20:21:00+08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-08-20T00:13:02+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The sun beats down on a heated Sunday afternoon; ideal time for a siesta following a heavy banana leaf lunch. Instead we pile in and trudge on to a unnamed field at a remote location to test out our aversion to heat. 4pm, a school somewhere in Taman Desa, Kuala Lumpur, a field and some footballs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After months of stalling, Mountview Rangers FC looked to get things going in sunny Malaysia and join the elite echelons of amateur football with the pipe dream of becoming an Oriental Ajax Academy for Gifted Youngsters, honing the powers of kids to supply the region with the best players. The reality is a rag-tag team of boys looking to kick a ball on a field instead of on a court, and a friendly was arranged to satisfy this need. If it exists, there is a market for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conceived by a South African-Indian living in Malaysia, Mountview Rangers has closer ties to Capetown than Kuala Lumpur having been named after a suburb in the city. The team itself is composed of mostly Malaysian boys aged 17-22, itching to shrug off futsal to experience the world of field football. Most of them have probably never had the opportunity, as Malaysian schools don’t typically provide too many footballing outlets while the proliferation of futsal continues to reign supreme. To play on a field with 10 other teammates against another full team can be considered something of a luxury, or an arduous effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, the latter. Amateur football teams depend greatly on numbers: enough players who are committed to the cause as well as financial support in the form of sponsorship and/or donations. Money is needed for match kits, ground rental, referees, and league registration, all this without giving any consideration to the formalities of training, coaching, exercise and tactics. Raising the money was tough enough, finally securing the help of less-than-anonymous donors while sourcing the services of isotonic drinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.30pm. The team finally trudges in. An inaugural ceremony of sorts is underway, giving out jerseys and numbers to each teammate followed by a round of warm applause. The beginning of our football club, at the best an opportunity to join the A leagues of the country and at the worst, a grassy outlet. Pictures ensue, decked out in our full kits right down to the shinpad. Picture with arms interlinked. Picture with arms folded. Picture with drink sponsor in hand. Picture with drink in one hand, thumbs up with the other. Picture drinking drink sponsor. We’ve run the gamut of pre-season long before any warm-up has take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5pm. The other team has trundled in. Today’s opponents are Butchers FC, a mixbag local-expat team seasoned in the lower rungs of the local leagues. The new season is upon them and they’re in need of a tune-up game to get back into shape, with the Rangers happy to oblige. Handshakes, pictures and warm-ups ensue as the heat cools, heralding the onset of evening as the players partake in a customary lap of the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what a field it was. Barely visible lines, random pieces of wood that look like mile markers, growths of mushroom where the penalty spot should be. One half of the pitch looks slightly larger than the other, the goals lack nets, the ground bumpy and uneven with more dirt than grass. In short, what you may come to expect from a school field. But it deters no one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5.30pm, we’re ready for kick-off. The referee and linesmen are nowhere in sight; a quick call reveals they’re waiting at a field 20 kilometers in a different direction. Comical as it was, substitutes from each team were readily drafted into refeering roles like this is something that happens with unfortunate regularity. The game starts with a shout (no whistle) and immediately the ball goes careening off the uneven ground, flying overhead as two players come together to head a ball that they miss completely. The scene looks more akin to rugby played with a round ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is played in 3 periods of 30 minutes with a 5-minute break in between to allow for water, rolling substitutions and novice fitness levels. The gulf in ability between the two teams immediately becomes apparent, not in terms of technical ability but with regards to football understanding. The Rangers may be well versed in the art of kicking but confined to futsal courts, there is a real lack of basic awareness of football from positioning to simple tactics. One doesn’t need to channel their inner Michels, just remember to keep a straight backline and stop playing opposing strikers onside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temperature reaches that glorious zone ideal for football. Butchers use their experience to plough forward, peppering the opposing defence with runs and dribbles that are dealt with in panicked hoofs to their forwards. The narrative seems to have set in: clear the ball at all costs and hope the strikers can conjure a chance from an awkward bounce. Butchers number 10, a Frenchman by the name of Emmanuel, takes up smart positions in front of the defence, causing all manner of problems for a vastly young and inexperienced team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10 minutes to go til the end of the first period and an awkward bounce determines the scoreline going into the break. A Butchers FC striker takes on a defender in the box only for the ball to flip flop off the turf and smack onto the defender’s hand. A handball shout from the striker. A handball shout from the ref. Penalty. Cooly slotted into the bottom left hand corner. A young defender deflated and cursing at the ground beneath him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First break. Drinks all around, the captain-manager tries to encourage his team. Substitutions are made, not for tactical reasons, but to ensure everyone gets to play. No room for toilet breaks. We go again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little bit of energy has been injected into the second half, as a football commentator might say. Smart interchanges between two of the Rangers players sees a couple of chances, but a quick counter and a smart finish sees the leading team go 2-0 up. Butchers FC are heckling their own player, a fairly overweight gentleman content to sit on the last defender and take pot shots at goal. Run a bit Shaun! Try and lose that spare tyre! It takes any ill will out of the game, a casual reminder to all that that the occasion is a friendly one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rangers have a set piece. A beauty of a cross is floated into the box, it’s met by a foot, it’s in the back of the non-existent net! The subs bench is elated. Mountview Rangers FC have their first goal ever, ever. The opposing team applauds the delivery and finish. Come on boys lets do that again! As the second period ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More drinks, more subs. The crowd, composed of wives, children, friends, donors, and a girl with her cat, stretch out and enjoy the evening. Hardly a break this time, as the sun threatens to set and rob the game of sight. Butchers continue to dominate and it pays off as they take a 3-1 lead. Pretty scripted ending to the game, as Rangers fling forward to try and add one more goal to their little history book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not today, as the sun sets and with it the game. Customary handshakes all around, everyone likes how that looks on TV and it feels as good as it should; like a sense of accomplishment and celebration regardless of the score. Mountview Rangers FC come away from the game disappointed by the outcome, as all boys want to do is win. But not much could be expected of inexperienced, untrained bunch of kids brought together by matching outfits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea was always to get things going, to start playing games against other teams, to feel the joy of grass beneath ones boots. There’s nothing like the space afforded by field football, the simple pleasure of rocketing a ball skyward, of set pieces. Mountview Rangers are a long way from being ready to join a league, but the numbers are there, the passion is present, the commitment is cemented. And finally at long last, so is the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Yoann Gourcuff: A Lament</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/secret-footballer/yoann-gourcuff-a-lament.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/secret-footballer/yoann-gourcuff-a-lament.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-19T09:46:00+08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-08-20T00:13:36+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;20-year old ‘wonderkid’ with a four-star scout rating. Slightly temperamental, moody even. Young, unknown and French, a technically sound attacking midfielder; Arsene Wenger would be proud. The decision to bring him to the club would seem like a no-brainer surely, and I better keep an eye on him in real life; Football Manager rarely gets these things wrong. Yoann Gourcuff was surely going to be a household name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had the build-up of a future superstar from playing position to cheekbones, and an early move to AC Milan seemed like the beginning of a glittering career laden with trophies, sponsorship deals, individual awards and an abundance of Youtube reels with millions of views. French legends and football contemporaries weighed in, Gourcuff is the most talented player of his generation, there is something magical about him, Gourcuff is the heir to Zidane. The heir to Zidane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le successeur. le phénonème Gourcuff, navigating his way on grass with the infamous weight of the French press and public waiting to envelope him. He should have known that the chances of his success essentially halved once the Z word was uttered; fulfilling the skill and technical ability of the man was one thing, but carrying the nation on the insoles of your feet was another entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t help that such comparisons were less lazy than true. He moved the ball in a way that anyone would romanticise as French: elegant and graceful, uncomplicated and effective. He typically used every square inch of his feet, especially conducting  with the insteps of his shoes, just as his famed predecessor did. He occupied the same space, the same role, as a playmaker that controlled transitions and attacks ruthlessly whenever the ball came to him, and it always came to him. His ability to find a pass was needle-like, he shrugged off opponents like a coat on a rainy day, he had a penchant for scoring the spectacular as Paris-Saint Germain and Romania witnessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He inherited the introvertness, shying away from the interviews fame brought, preferring the solace of solitude and the sanctity of the self. He rubbed egos incorrectly with his apathy and lack of mollycoddling; the end of his Italian summer was fated when the demi-god Maldini decreed “Gourcuff in Milan was 100% wrong”, citing behavioural issues that hinted at a player who had problems with conviviality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retour. Bordeaux was the platform, just as it had been for Zizou all those years ago, and Gourcuff found the feet that was expected of him. 15 goals. 15 assists. Goal of the Season. Ligue 1 Player of the Year. A modest 20th for the Ballon D’Or. Gourcuff was undeniably the new darling of French football with his film star looks and the World Cup 2010 as his set. The weight was surely at its heaviest now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That tournament will always be a watershed moment for French footballing history - for the poorest of reasons. A evil pantomime played out by the villainous Domenech, Anelka, Evra and Ribery. The Bordeaux man was conspired against and thrown aside, turned into a national scapegoat with the extension of an elbow and a subsequent red card. The big egos of France refused to play ball with Gourcuff, both literally and metaphorically, as he was shunned as a non-believer off the field and deliberately excluded from play off it. His inwardness was not good enough for the French big wigs, his inheritance deemed false, and when the curtains came crashing down on the campaign it took Gourcuff along with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He lost his place in the French team and in the hearts of the French masses. The heir to Zidane had bitterly disappointed, crushed under the weight of expectation, the failures of the national team and smothered by his people, his teammates, his media. A big money move to Lyon prior to the tournament did nothing to help, where the failings of the World Cup were exacerbated by a dramatic dip in form and injury. Gourcuff had his crown taken from him before it was modified for fitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He struggled to capture the form and imagination that had led to the trumpet heralds singing his name. Little niggles made it difficult for him to retain a place in the team, and the emergence of a new playmaker prince in the form of young Clement Grenier further pushed him to the fringes, bordering on Almost Famous territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dust on the international stage had settled but Gourcuff was still reeling, injured from the nuclear fallout. Domenech’s successor, one Laurent Blanc entered the fold as national manager but Gourcuff failed to lock down a place, while Blanc opted for the nifty abilities of Samir Nasri or Mathieu Valbuena instead. Yohan Cabaye occupied the playmaker role from deep, looking to control the play, spread passes across the pitch and join the attack late, as France seemed to gravitate away from the tactics that made Zidane king. Gourcuff missed the entirety of the 2011-2012 season through injury and was subsequently omitted from Euro 2012. There was no place for him to assume and Messrs Ribery and Evra were still around, lending to the belief that Blanc opted for squad unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new understudy. A minor role for Lyon, second to Grenier as the new Frenchman began to stereotypically court Anglo-Saxon teams in the Premier League. Flashes of brilliance hindered by injury and a lack of confidence, he was once again overlooked by Deschamps’ France. A muted 2012-2013 season; Gourcuff now is known only among the Lyon faithful and Youtube connoisseurs. The man once heralded for his inheritance is no longer even spuriously linked with a move to Arsenal, personifying a post-Zidane French footballer whose world has turned against him and cast him asunder.
 
2014 brings a new age. At 28, Gourcuff has finally shrugged both his injury concerns and the weight of Normandy from his shoulders; a chance to finally become the player the world was promised. The ability is undoubted, undeniable. His mental fortitude, one can hope has steeled with age. For France and the national team it may be too little too late, but there is yet a point to make to the world. Gourcuff was great, he is great. But he’s short of time to prove it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Curious Case of – Martín Palermo</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/secret-footballer/the-curious-case-of-martin-palermo.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/secret-footballer/the-curious-case-of-martin-palermo.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-19T09:44:00+08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-08-21T14:57:11+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The goals I scored were normal, Palermo makes miracles.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Diego Maradona&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A folk hero to Boca Juniors, Championship Manager players, and to some extent, Argentina, Martín Palermo was a player who never quite hit the heights he seemed destined for, but is still remembered fondly by those he impacted with his passionate performances on the pitch. At his testimonial, a packed La Bombonera turned out to salute the Boca legend with all the vigour of a Copa Libertadores final. After the game had finished, a tearful Palermo embraced family members and delivered a heartfelt speech to the Boca faithful as forklifts uprooted one of the goals. It was quickly wrapped with a blue and gold bow before Boca presented it to Palermo. An unorthodox present perhaps, but it was a testament to the high regard in which his club held him. What Naohiro Takahara would give for a sliver of his success…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More cherished in Argentina than Lionel Messi, El Loco is certainly deserving of the status, even if this is implausible to outsiders who will only remember him for his infamous hat-trick of missed penalties. Never the best technically, Palermo developed an unerring sense of positioning, enabling him to seemingly always be in the right place at the right time. If thoughts of Inzaghi come to mind, Palermo was certainly much more of an all-rounder, possessing a bullet of a header and playing an integral role in link-up play with his ability to hold up the ball. Using his foot, head, chest, knee, or seemingly any appendage, Palermo would score with any part of his body; fans on both sides declared him touched by a magic wand (a fact he embraced) due to the perceived luck and undoubted misfortune he suffered during the course of his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a tragedy would unfold in 2006, when his son, Stefano, tragically passed away. Declining time off, he insisted on playing that very weekend in a league match against Banfield. As fans had come to expect, Palermo did not veer from the script in the slightest, duly scoring twice as Boca Juniors emerged victorious. Substituted amidst a sea of emotion and the respect of the entire stadium, the burly striker trudged off the field having tearily paid his own small tribute to his fallen son. Such moments would endear him to the Argentinian public, but it was not the first or the last time he would touch their hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/Ags1HJVIIYw?start=649" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a country where technique and elegance is cherished and exalted, Palermo proved that heart and passion can win over the most hardened fan. He would make his international debut in 1999, having recently won the South American Footballer of the Year award in 1998 and finished as a Primera División champion with Boca. Things looked bright for the young man from La Plata, and he was called up to the Argentina squad for the 1999 Copa América. Scoring twice in Argentina’s opening match to defeat Ecuador 3-1, he could hardly have asked for a better tournament debut. However, disaster would strike in the next match against Colombia, as Palermo missed three penalties during the match, with the Colombians running out 3-0 winners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/SWm6nQtbWK8?start=15" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a moment that, for many fans, would define his career, and is how he is ostensibly remembered by them to this day. Argentina would defeat Uruguay 2-0 in their next match, with Palermo again getting on the scoresheet but by now, he had obtained the dubious honour of holding the world record for the most missed penalties in an international. As a result of failing to top their group, Argentina would meet Brazil in the quarterfinals, losing 2-1. It would be 10 long years before Palermo would don the Albiceleste jersey again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of a sudden, the hottest young player in world football was no longer in demand. The raft of European clubs that had been queuing up for his services, most notably Lazio, slipped away quietly. He also suffered a serious knee injury in November in a match against Colón, a series of blows devastating enough to destroy any footballer’s career. But not Palermo. In that very same match, he remarkably played on, despite tearing the cruciate ligaments in his knee and even managed to score his 100th career goal. The injury would keep him out of action for seven months. Working his way back to full fitness, the stage could hardly have been better set for his return – a Copa Libertadores quarterfinal against their archrivals, River Plate. Coming on as a substitute, he latched onto a dangerous ball played into the penalty area. As the River defence backed off, Palermo placed the ball beyond the keeper with his left foot, sealing a 3-0 victory and sparking wild celebrations among the Boca contingent, with Carlos Bianchi beaming on the sidelines. Boca would go on to win the tournament, their first Copa Libertadores in 22 years. Later that year, Boca Juniors would defeat Real Madrid in the Intercontinental Cup, with Palermo grabbing both goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/pgc-lelpbeM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European clubs slowly sat up and took note of his fine return to form. At over six feet tall with an immaculate sense of positioning and heading, Palermo was a typical European striker on paper and his combination of speed and strength were favoured traits on the continent. Napoli were credited with an interest, having offered Palermo a loan deal till the end of the season. However, the only club to make a bid for him was lowly Villarreal, who eventually secured his signature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fuck me. Palermo can do better than that,” quipped Maradona, echoing the thoughts of millions of Argentinians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Palermo’s time in Europe would prove to be a massive disappointment. Struggling for form, Palermo must have thought his luck had turned when scoring a rare goal and instinctively went to celebrate with the Villarreal supporters. Perversely, the magic wand that seemed to hover over his shoulder struck again, with the supporters causing a separating wall to collapse on him. Palermo’s leg was crushed, broken in two places. He would take almost a year to recover from this latest setback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to the team in 2002, he never really made the same impact he did for Boca, and by 2003, he was shipped off to Real Betis where the same story played out. He would end his playing days in Spain at second division side Alavés before making his way back to Boca Juniors in the summer of 2004. No one could explain it. How could Palermo, a burly poacher with a keen nose for goal flop in Spain? It was certainly not caused by culture or language barriers. Perhaps he really was cursed after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not that Boca fans were complaining though, as their hero instantly assimilated back into the team and continued from where he left off in 2001, winning several more league titles and another Copa Libertadores in 2007. He even found his way into the Guiness Book of World Records again, this time for the longest headed goal (his 200th goal for Boca), a record he would hold until it was broken by Jone Samuelson in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/w_EO1bX2Gf4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps his greatest moment of redemption came in the 2010 World Cup qualifiers. Recalled to the Argentina side by Maradona, some sections of the public were not too keen on an aging poacher spearheading their side. In the penultimate game of the qualifiers against Peru, the tie was finely poised at 0-0 when Maradona decided to bring the 35-year old on, ahead of Sergio Agüero and Carlos Tevez. Despite Gonzalo Higuaín giving Argentina the lead, Peru equalised in the 90th minute, to level the score at 1-1, leaving Argentina in serious danger of failing to qualify for the World Cup. With a final flourish, Argentina found themselves with a corner. Peru failed to clear their lines and Messi put in a low cross which took a deflection, but somehow found its way to Palermo at the far post, leaving El Loco with the simplest task of tapping the ball in for a 93rd minute winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/NLUwV1S1j-g" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cue mass pandemonium. Palermo reeled away in delight and relief, ripping off his shirt as his teammates mobbed him. Cameras cut away to Maradona sliding across the pitch on his belly before panning back to Palermo cutting a lone figure in the torrential rain. With his arms spread wide, he looked to the heavens, soaking up the glory of his very own Shawshank Redemption moment. Argentina would go on to defeat Uruguay in their final qualifier to secure their place in the 2010 World Cup, a tournament which Palermo would be part of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was incomparable because it was for the national team at a time like this. I don't know if it was fate but I thank God for this triumph.” – Martín Palermo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In South Africa, Palermo would come on as an 80th minute substitute for Diego Milito in the final group game against Greece. Towards the end of the game, Messi went on a jinking run, evading several defenders before firing away a shot which the Greek goalkeeper could only parry into the path of Palermo. Pouncing on the rebound, he made no mistake and slotted home past the Greek keeper with his weaker right foot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/XB5VIbBU3WA?start=162" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reeling away in delight, his face told a story of a man once vilified but now fully redeemed. His teammates mobbed him as he celebrated, sharing in the emotional moment for a legend of the Argentinian club game; this was a man held in high esteem by his peers. As his teammates assumed their positions, he made his way to the touchline, sharing a warm embrace with Maradona as the two Boca legends celebrated his achievement. The goal ensured he became the first Boca player to score at the World Cup for 80 years, while he also became Argentina’s oldest goalscorer of all-time at 36 years of age, breaking the record held by none other than Maradona.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final goal of his career came in a league match against relegation favourites, Quilmes. With Boca 2-0 down, Palermo once again waved his magic wand and scored a stunning piledriver to bring Boca back into the game. The comeback would be completed four minutes later, with the match finishing 2-2. Palermo would end his career as Boca Juniors’ leading goalscorer of all-time, finishing with an impressive tally of 236 goals from 404 matches. He is also the joint fourth-highest goalscorer of all time in the Primera División.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/oV_Nhzp9z-Q" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps, the true indication of the legacy of Saint Palermo lies at the museum of La Bombonera. There, a statue of El Loco standing over three metres tall hovers over visitors to the Museo de la Pasión Boquense – one of three in the club museum. The other two statues? Diego Maradona and Juan Román Riquelme. In a final defiant act mirroring the narrative of his career, Palermo once again finds himself in the right place at the right time. Forever.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Of Lobanovskyi and Kyiv</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/secret-footballer/of-lebanovskyi-and-kyiv.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/secret-footballer/of-lebanovskyi-and-kyiv.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-19T09:41:00+08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-08-21T14:57:11+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“With a little work, you can break down Valeriy Lobanovskyi's background and find the answers that explain why he was one of the greatest footballing minds ever. He was a naturally gifted footballer, albeit very much an individualist and that, ultimately, taught him the value of the collective.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Gabriele Marcotti&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the achievements of the collective was the ultimate yardstick by which the great Valeriy Lobanovskyi measured his career. The legendary Ukrainian manager is synonymous with Dynamo Kyiv, the team he managed for most of his career and where he achieved his greatest successes in management. Two Cup Winners’ Cups and a UEFA Super Cup is no mean feat, especially with clubs taking the former (now defunct) competition very seriously in those days. Aside from his role in transforming Dynamo Kyiv into one of the most feared and technically proficient sides on the continent, Lobanovskyi’s role in marrying sport and science had a huge impact on the modern game, with many of today’s philosophies borne directly from his innovative methodologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He first took over Dynamo Kyiv in 1974, after a spell at Dnipro Dnipropetrovsk which saw them get promoted to the Soviet Top League. Dynamo would come calling and Lobanovskyi would pack his bags for his beloved club where he would stay for the next 17 years, in between three spells in charge of the USSR. Breaking the dominance of Russian clubs, by the end of his tenure, Dynamo Kiev were the most successful team in the history of the Soviet Top League with 13 league titles to their name, eight of which were contributed by Lobanovskyi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="philosophy-and-ideology"&gt;Philosophy and Ideology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lobanovskyi was a rare breed of manager – he was formerly a player of some repute, but he also had the vision to study and implement new tactics and methods devised through scientific means to create the optimum footballing machine. He would go on to outshine his mentor, Viktor Maslov, who was Lobanovskyi’s main influence. The Russian was noted for inventing the 4-4-2 formation, and having first introduced the pressing game so prevalent in today’s game, but was lightyears ahead of his time. Having learnt and seen first-hand the influence of science on sport, Lobanovskyi would continue his coach’s work to the point of obsession, with players constituting specific elements in the compound that was Dynamo Kyiv. No deviation was necessary (or even allowed), with the Ukrainian expecting every member of his team to follow his instructions to the letter. Of course, this was only in the positional sense. Every member of the team was required to know how to play in any position on the pitch – the Soviet answer to total football if you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possessing a degree in thermal engineering and having been coached by one of the most forward thinking managers of the time in Maslov, perhaps it is no surprise that Lobanovskyi took a scientific approach when it came to dissecting football. It was around the same time when computers began to make their way into everyday life, and he quickly realised the potential of collecting and computing data to be analysed and used for matchday preparations. While at Dnipro, Lobanovskyi met Anatoliy Zelentsov, a professor at the Institute of Physical science who was a keen statistician. The two would form one of football’s most intelligent partnerships of all-time, devising a scientific approach to each matchday and reducing every aspect of Dynamo’s game to a number that would correlate into data. Their tactical beliefs were outlined in a book they co-wrote, “In The Methodological Basis of the Development of Training Models”, where the key feature of Dynamo’s pressing game was outlined – the full-press, half-press and false-press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lobanovskyi realised early on that full pressing would enable Dynamo to win the ball back in their opponents’ half, which would enable them to retain possession – the most crucial aspect of any football game. His ideas revolved around possession. Attack and defence were only relative to possession; positions on the pitch was not a relevant factor in the equation. In order to attack, the opposition must be relieved of the ball, which in short was the mantra of each of his three styles of pressing. Full-pressing was reserved for technically gifted opposition, where they would be forced to think quickly or risk losing the ball, which happened more often than not. Once the opposition grew accustomed to the pressing, he would switch to false-pressing, where only one man would press the player in possession, which would force him into a mistake when releasing the ball, with Dynamo retrieving possession once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To Lobanovskyi, football was a system that comprised of 22 elements, with each subsystem of 11 moving around in their areas of the pitch, with laws dictating what could be done and what could not. In theory, if Dynamo were to come up a team that played exactly like them, the two subsystems would cancel each other out and the match would end in a draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The first thing we have in mind is to strive for new courses of action that will not allow the opponent to adapt to our style of play. If an opponent has adjusted himself to our style of play and found a counterplay, then we need to find a new strategy. That is the dialectic of the game. You have to go forward in such a way and with such a range of attacking options that it will force the opponent to make a mistake. In other words, it’s necessary to force the opponent into the condition you want them to be in.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Valeriy Lobanovskyi&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, Lobanovskyi discovered early on the importance of strength and stamina in his teams, as well as mental capacity. His use of computers was integral to the preparations. Mountains of statistics were compiled and players would be subjected to intense physical training sessions as well as mental tests. Players were expected to memorise the positions of all teammates across the pitch; in the event that a player found himself in a foreign position, he would be able to play the ball to a teammate effortlessly and quickly, giving the opposition no time to react. This training style created a team of physically and intellectually superior players – the exact type of player Lobanovskyi required to ensure optimum results from his pressing system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Players have to react faster. Every moment, every action happens faster. Think faster, act faster – this is the football of the future.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Valeriy Lobanovskyi&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results certainly backed up his methods, even if not all of his players took kindly to them. Winning the Soviet League eight times certainly proved his credentials as a manager, especially with Dynamo being the only Ukrainian club to pose a threat to the dominance of larger, wealthier Russian clubs. Club legends such as Oleg Blokhin, Igor Belanov and Andriy Shevchenko all thrived under his tutelage, with each of them going on to win the prestigious Ballon d’Or in their careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the culmination of his footballing philosophy came in the final of the 1986 Cup Winner’s Cup final against Atlético Madrid. 11 years prior, Dynamo won the same tournament by beating Ferencvárosi in the final, becoming the first Soviet club to win a European trophy much to the chagrin of their Russian counterparts. Already a goal up, Dynamo’s second goal came as a result of a swift counterattack. Running down the left wing, Vasyl Rats would switch the ball to the right, where Belanov swiftly controlled the ball before switching it to the right again. As the ball reached him, Vadym Yevtushenko played a first-time lob to the right where Blokhin lifted the ball over the onrushing goalkeeper for a wonderful second goal. It took about 10 seconds to get the ball from their half into their opponent’s goal, with a move resembling a windshield wiper’s swift sweeping motion. The goal embodied the very ideology championed by Lobanovskyi throughout his career – fast, fluid, simple. In football, two plus two very rarely equals four, but on that night in the Stade de Gerland, Lobanovskyi came as close as anyone to solving the complex science that is football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/_EZa9Oet2Mk?start=357" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a triumph that would prove to be the pinnacle of his career. Further Soviet Top League titles would follow, as well as a defeat in the final of the 1988 European Championship thanks to a bullet header from Ruud Gullit and Marco van Basten’s volleyed wonder goal. Two undistinguished spells would follow in the UAE and Kuwait, with Lobanovskyi returning home to Dynamo for a second spell in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="the-second-coming"&gt;The Second Coming&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps his second spell at the club would prove to be his greatest unheralded achievement. Having rejoined in January 1997, he set about stabilising the club and optimising the talented young squad he had at his disposal. Shevchenko and Sergei Rebrov were the marksmen, Aleksandr Khatsekevich and Valentin Belkevich ran the show in the middle, while Oleg Luzhny and Kakha Kaladze marshalled the backline. The sextet would be core members of his final great team that won five consecutive league titles between 1997 and 2001. But it is their European exploits that brought them all to the consciousness of the football world. Early indications were served in the 97/98 Champions League, where Dynamo Kyiv reached the quarterfinals, spearheaded by the deadly striking partnership formed by Rebrov and Shevchenko. This run including a 4-0 thrashing of Barcelona at the Nou Camp, with the irrepressible Shevchenko grabbing a hat-trick and Dynamo’s pressing pattern forcing Barcelona to play the game on their terms. The last real team formed under his philosophy of the collective, Lobanovskyi would prepare Dynamo for an assault on Europe the following season, one that very nearly altered the course of one of the most iconic moments in Champions League history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having only gained a single point from their opening two matches in the 98/99 Champions League, Dynamo could not afford to lose their third game, against the English champions Arsenal. Losing 1-0 in the third minute of added time, Rebrov found himself in acres of space and made no mistake, firing past the hapless David Seaman to secure a morale-boosting draw for Dynamo. It was the last point they would drop in the group phase, winning three consecutive games, including a 3-1 victory over a shell-shocked Arsenal, to top the group and qualify for the quarterfinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/bwvU2k1vqAs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawn against the defending champions, Dynamo were certainly the underdogs going into the tie, with Real Madrid’s legion of superstars including the likes of Roberto Carlos, Clarence Seedorf and Fernando Redondo among others. But as with the rest of his career, Lobanovskyi would champion the effectiveness of the collective over the individual, even if he did have players who had that extra spark of magic at his disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Bernabéu, Dynamo would take the lead thanks to the electrifying pace of Shevchenko who ran beyond the defence and finished unerringly past Bodo Illgner’s near post with the outside of his right foot. A curtain of silence fell over the stunned Bernabéu before Real quickly regrouped, equalising through Predrag Mijatović’s freekick, leaving the tie finely poised going into the second leg in Kyiv. With the away goal advantage, 80,000 fans crammed into the Olimpiyskiy National Sports Complex to cheer on their heroes. Dynamo held firm in spite of the visitors dominating, before Belkevich put Shevchenko through on goal, only for Illgner to catch the striker, conceding a penalty. He would miss the initial attempt, but quickly pounced on the rebound to give Dynamo the lead. 11 minutes from time, Rebrov scooped the ball over the Real defence, before Shevchenko expertly brought the ball down with his chest and finishing past Illgner to secure Dynamo’s place in the semifinals for the third time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a sense of destiny for Lobanovskyi, having previous failed at the semifinal stage of the competition back in 1977 and 1987. Having taken out the defending champions, Dynamo were confident of defeating Bayern Munich to progress to their first ever final. The first leg in Kyiv went smoothly, with Dynamo breezing into a 3-1 leads thanks to goals from Shevchenko and Vitaliy Kosovsky. With Bayern up against the ropes, Dynamo could sense blood and in the 62nd minute Kosovsky found himself alone in front of goal with only Oliver Kahn to beat. Going against the philosophy of Lobanovskyi, he opted for the delicate chip – a trait of the individual. The ball narrowly cleared the bar and Dynamo blew their chance for a 4-1 lead. Sensing the change of tide, Bayern upped the ante and scored two goals in the final 12 minutes to escape Kyiv with a barely believable 3-3 draw. Bayern would win the return leg 1-0 with a goal from Mario Basler, eliminating Dynamo from the competition, and with it, Lobanovskyi’s shot at lifting Ol’ Big Ears. With the way Manchester United played in the final, it is not inconceivable to think that Dynamo’s pressing game would have caused them problems aplenty. Sir Alex Ferguson was not particularly renowned for his advanced tactics in Europe and Lobanovskyi certainly would have had the upper hand in the final. The 1999 Champions League could have had such a different story were it not for Kosovsky’s ill-fated miss, and the Treble may have simply been one of football’s great what ifs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That fateful night in Kyiv would prove to be the final hurrah for the team, with Shevchenko departing for Milan while Luzhny packed up for Arsenal. Rebrov would head for England in 2000 and Kaladze would join up with Shevchenko in 2001. Milan were also credited with an interest in Belkevich, but ultimately, the move never occurred for the fine Belarussian playmaker. Dynamo would never be the same again, and although they almost beat Real Madrid to a quarterfinal place in the 99/00 Champions League, only losing out on their head-to-head record, they would never come close to emulating their previous season’s run again. To date, Dynamo are the last side from the Eastern Bloc to have reached the semifinal or better; no club has come close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="post-1999"&gt;Post 1999&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lobanovskyi would die doing what he loved most, leading Dynamo Kiev to victory. Shortly after defeating Metalurg Zaporizhzhya, the legendary manager would suffer a stroke on May 7, 2002. During a brain surgery six days later, Ukraine would lose one of their most beloved sons. Dynamo Kyiv would rename their stadium after him in a show of respect and appreciation for his service to the club. Over 200,000 people would attend his state funeral, including Shevchenko and various alumni of the great Dynamo teams of the 70’s and 80’s, mourning a man who had not only transformed Dynamo, but football as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact Lobanovskyi had made on a young Shevchenko was never forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lobanovskyi was like a father to me. I would like to score a goal and dedicate it to him. It would be fantastic for Milan and me if it helped us to reach the Champions League final,” he reflected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He duly scored the away goal against Inter that clinched Milan’s place in the final, before slotting home the winning penalty in the final shootout, securing the Champions League that Lobanovskyi had so dearly craved. Flying back to Kyiv at the first opportunity, Shevchenko would place the giant trophy and his winner’s medal on his former coach’s grave, captured in a poignant image. A year later, Shevchenko would return to grave to share his Ballon d’Or award with his fallen mentor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shadow of Lobanovskyi was again cast over Ukraine during EURO 2012, where the home nation was led by Blokhin and captained by Shevchenko, who duly delivered a final heroic cameo, scoring a brace in a 2-1 comeback victory over Sweden. Perhaps more fittingly, Ukraine’s style of play resembled a team focused on the collective, much like Lobanovskyi’s teams of years gone by, albeit a less talented version, but an homage to the great man nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Wilson talks about the impact of Lobanovskyi in a great article from &lt;a href="http://www.theguardian.com/football/blog/2011/may/12/valeriy-lobanovskyi-dynamo-kyiv"&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt;, where a tidy little anecdote emerges that summarises the man. During a visit to the Science and Research Institute of the Construction Industry after winning the league, he shared a short exchange with the scientist Volodymyr Sabaldyr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes, we have won the league. But so what? Sometimes we played badly. We just got more points than other teams who played worse than us. I can't accept your praise as there are no grounds for it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabaldyr asked him how it felt to achieve something that had been a dream for Kyivans for decades. “A realised dream ceases to be a dream,” Lobanovskyi replied. “What is your dream as a scientist? Your degree? Your doctorate? Your post-doctoral thesis?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Maybe,” Sabaldyr replied. “But a real scientist dreams about making a contribution to scientific development, about leaving his mark on it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;”And there you have your answer.”&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Are South American Strikers In A League of Their Own</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/articles/secret-footballer/are-south-american-strikers-in-a-league-of-their-own.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/articles/secret-footballer/are-south-american-strikers-in-a-league-of-their-own.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-19T09:34:00+08:00</published>
    <updated>2014-08-21T11:40:13+08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I have said many times that Europe still produces many fantastic football players, but if you look well we do not produce strikers well.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Arsène Wenger&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview last year, the Arsenal manager went on record stating that he believed South America currently produces the best strikers in the world. A quick glance at a list of top strikers in Europe certainly seems to add weight to his claims, with the likes of Neymar, Radamel Falcao, Sergio Agüero, Luis Suárez and Lionel Messi undoubtedly among the world’s greatest marksmen. Their lesser known countrymen also ply their trade in many of Europe’s weaker leagues, as well as around the world in outposts from Canada to Qatar to Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South America has always been known worldwide for their steady supply of coffee, sugar, corn, and wheat; since the turn of the century, footballers have quickly been added to that list, with increasing numbers of top talents leaving the continent at earlier ages for a shot at stardom while the lesser lights make their way abroad simply to feed their families back home. Whichever way you look at it, South Americans are a constant in most, if not all, football leagues globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to focus on the greatest, we must look to Europe. It is universally agreed that all the greats have plied their trade in Europe for a period of time, with very rare exceptions being made for the likes of Pelé. In the modern era, European football is the primary diet of television screens worldwide, allowing cash rich clubs to sweep up the best talents from across the world, thus creating a level of competition not found anywhere else in the world. So where do South Americans strikers lie in the grand scheme of things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="does-european-club-football-define-talent"&gt;Does European Club Football Define Talent?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past 47 European league seasons, South Americans have only won the European Golden Shoe 10 times; however, nine of those winners have come in the last 18 years, coinciding with the increase in South American talent across the continent. Perhaps more tellingly, in the last eight Champions League seasons, five of the Golden Boot winners have been South Americans, with only Cristiano Ronaldo bucking the trend. Rough numbers, but an indication of the changing times nonetheless. When you consider that Argentina’s haul of six European Cup / Champions League top scorers awards belong to only two of the greatest footballers of all time – Alfredo Di Stéfano and Messi – there is a more compelling case to present for the potency of South American strikers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For every Messi, there is a Martín Palermo – a talent that thrived at home but never did quite make the cut with the big boys in Europe. The sheer numbers imported to European leagues ensure that there will be some flops but the numbers bandied around by clubs suggest that this is a risk worth taking, evidenced by the big moves this summer which has already seen Alexis Sánchez and Suárez swap leagues amidst much fanfare and huge fees, with Falcao possibly moving on as well. It was a similar story in 2013, as Falcao and Edinson Cavani graced Ligue 1 with their presence and massive price tags, while Gonzalo Higuaín made a big-money move to Napoli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the biggest statement of intent last season came from Barcelona, who stumped up €57m to sign Neymar from Santos, in a record transfer between a South American and European club. The astonishing outlay was made even more astounding by the fact that Neymar had only ever played in Brazil, a league not known for its defensive qualities, which serves to illustrate the gambles European clubs are willing to take on South American striking talents. Another £30m transfer, Erik Lamela, has yet to shine for Tottenham Hotspur, and he didn’t even move directly from Argentina, which further highlights the risk involved when signing premium South American talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of Europe’s top leagues, it can be argued that the only one that South Americans have yet to crack is the English Premier League, but in recent seasons, the deadly finishing and high work rate of Carlos Tevez, Agüero and Suárez has suggested that South Americans are close to conquering their final frontier of world football. The likes of Ignacio Scocco continue to provide ammunition for the naysayers, but the signs are that they are almost there. Last season, Suárez became the first South American to finish as the Premier League’s top goalscorer, an astonishing stat when you consider that fellow South Americans like Sonny Anderson, Hernán Crespo, fat Ronaldo and Giovane Élber have been running away with the rest of Europe’s goalscoring charts on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact South American strikers have made in Europe is undeniable, and clubs are always increasingly putting their faith in these fine marksmen. A quick glance at UEFA’s club coefficient provides numbers that back up this notion; of the top 50 clubs in the rankings, 50% of them have a South American striker on the payroll. Considering that clubs like Fiorentina, Monaco and Borussia Mönchengladbach are not even part of the top 50, it certainly speaks volumes about the importance of South American hitmen in the European club game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="implications-of-a-south-american-upbringing"&gt;Implications of A South American Upbringing?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With many South American strikers (and players in general) having grown up and risen out of poverty, slums and general hardship, the hunger created almost definitely plays a pivotal role in their desire and push for success. Suárez may revile football fans worldwide for his “competitiveness”, but what if his rationale of success at all costs really has an ingrown, cognitive trigger? If we were to focus on less controversial examples, the likes of Tevez, Diego Maradona and Marcelo Salas all grew up in dire lack in comparison to their European counterparts. Brazil can count Ronaldo, Romário, and Pelé as part of the “underprivileged” club. All of them would grow up to become key strikers for club and country, making a huge impact on European and world football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from a hunger generally not found in Europe, the role of futsal in South America has long been recognised and lauded as a key part of youth training, and it is a wonder that very few European countries actively encourage youth players to pick it up. The lack of technical ability in England has been debated for years, and yet a key training too like futsal continues to be ignored. The national futsal side languishes at 70 in the futsal world rankings, behind luminaries such as Malaysia and Turkmenistan. Higher up the futsal rankings, the top 20 teams in the world reads like a who’s who of countries known for their technically superior players. Why is it that Europeans, for the most part, continue to ignore the indoor game? Although many European teams find themselves in the top 20, it is rare to hear of futsal being used regularly to train youngsters to improve their close control, dribbling, and quick thinking among other key skills useful in the 11-a-side game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe produces its fair share of good strikers, but they tend to be one dimensional – very good at one or two things. Think Filippo Inzaghi, the man who was born offside. Think Ruud van Nistelrooy, the master finisher. Very rarely will you find a South American version of these two deadly strikers; their representatives tend to come in a more explosive package complete with close control and fabulous dribbling ability. With the exception of Ciro Immobile, the top scorers in Europe’s big five leagues this season are all well-rounded strikers who do much more than put the ball in the back of the net (Ronaldo, Suárez, Robert Lewandowski, Zlatan Ibrahimović). Although most of them are European, they are also exceptions to the rule and reflect the state of the game today which require a complete striker possessing an impressive repertoire of skills. Little wonder then why clubs are so willing to splash the cash on technically gifted South American frontmen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In the summer, you had Falcao going to Monaco, Cavani going to PSG in a big transfer, Suarez everybody wanted to buy him, Higuain has gone to Napoli for a lot of money, but in Europe that is an area where it is difficult to find. In Germany, I can remember in every club you had a big striker, they produced some fantastic ones, but they do not produce young strikers. Is that a consequence of the way we coach? Of modern life? I do not know.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Arsène Wenger&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id="international-proving-grounds"&gt;International Proving Grounds&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Club football is one spectrum of the argument; perhaps it is international football where South America shines the most. At the World Cup, only 4.5 slots out of 32 are allocated to CONMEBOL teams (2014 is an exception as Brazil were hosts), meaning that South American teams regularly make up only 15.6% of the total teams in the tournament. Earlier tournaments may have had a lesser number of teams, but South American have never made up the majority of the participants, save for the 1930 edition. In fact, early editions of the World Cup held in Europe saw very few teams from South America taking part due to the distance, with only two countries taking part in the 1934 and 1954 World Cups, while Brazil were the lone South American team present in 1938.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 20 editions of the World Cup, a South American has won the Golden Boot seven times – a respectable 35%, suggesting that their strikers are often punching above their weight mathematically. Furthermore, in the 2014 World Cup, 43 goals out of 171 (25.1%) were scored by South Americans while in the 2010 World Cup, they accounted for 35 goals out of 145 (24.1%). The average percentage of goals scored by South Americans in the three World Cups before 2010 is a measly 18.7%; this lends further weight to Wenger’s claims about modern European strikers not being up to par. If we take a look at the World Cup finals in its entirety, South Americans have scored 558 of the 2,379 goals to date (23.4%), while accounting for only 79 of 425 total spots for teams (18.6%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further down the footballing food chain, the U20 World Cup provides several interesting numbers to draw rough conclusions from. In 19 editions of the youth tournament, a South American team has triumphed 11 times, and have failed to produce a finalist on only five occasions. Narrowing in on goalscorers, a South American has picked up the Golden Shoe nine times, with the other 10 being won by players from all other confederations combined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick look at the winners and runners-up of the Golden Shoe show that the South Americans seemingly go on to become top level forwards of some repute, including the likes of Messi, Agüero, Javier Saviola, Adriano, and a certain Maradona. From the other confederations, only Davor Šuker and David Trezeguet stand out (despite only claiming the Silver Shoe), and even then, the latter is of Argentinian descent and began his career in the country with Platense. Meanwhile, other Golden Shoe winners such as Pablo Couñago and Dominic Adiyiah have faded into oblivion, their early promise snuffed out rapidly at the top level of the game. The Golden Shoe is no indicator of pending South American greatness, as Henrique (2011) and Adaílton (1997) would testify, but the emerging talents from that confederation seemingly make a better fist of it than their counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="on-importing-talent"&gt;On Importing Talent&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before South Americans began flooding European leagues en masse, the likes of Italy and Spain already began naturalising “citizens”, born abroad to immigrants but called back to play for their “country”. Italy has a long history of naturalised oriundo, players who were fast-tracked to the national side and hastily given passports on the strength of their ancestry, a topic excellently summarised in the &lt;a href="http://inbedwithmaradona.com/journal/2012/7/20/a-brief-history-of-the-oriundo.html"&gt;In Bed With Maradona blog&lt;/a&gt;. Many South American countries boast a huge population that can trace their Italian heritage, and knowing this, Italy capitalised to strengthen their national team. At the time, the Italian government allowed rapid “repatriation” for anyone of Italian descent, and this paved the way for Raimundo Orsi and Enrique Guaita to represent Italy at the 1934 World Cup, playing key roles as the Azzurri lifted their first world title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In later years, Juan Alberto Schiaffino, Omar Sivori, and José Altafini would win two World Cups and a Copa América between them, before packing their bags for a one-way ticket to Italy to embrace a new future and a new national team. Although no longer widespread, the practice is still in place today, with the likes of Amauri, and most recently, Pablo Osvaldo, among Italy’s latest oriundi strikers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even Spain have imported South American talent to play for their national team, most notably the legendary Di Stéfano, who donned the red of Spain between 1957 and 1961, amassing 31 caps and scoring 23 times. Other notable names include the Argentinians, Juan Antonia Pizzi and José Eulogio Gárate, and the less successful Brazilians, Catanha and Diego Costa, although the latter still has time on his side. The practice of naturalising South Americans has caught on in recent times, with several countries securing forwards of South American descent to help out their national teams, including Croatia’s Eduardo and Germany’s Cacau.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="does-south-america-produce-the-best-strikers"&gt;Does South America Produce the Best Strikers?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The facts have been presented, and a case can certainly be made for this theory. Although it can be argued that South American strikers regularly punch above their weight in European club football and at international level, the disparity in numbers mean that it is unlikely that the debate will be conclusively settled by one confederation outperforming another. To conclusively identify and elevate a single component of a football team supplied by a particular continent is to shoehorn the history of the game into a few concrete numbers. It can be said that the current trend does indicate a South American stranglehold on talented forwards in world football, but throughout history, there have been plenty of legendary European forwards such as Francisco Gento, Silvio Piolo, Raúl, and chief among them, Ferenc Puskás.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talent is subjective, greatness even more so. Football can be described in numbers, but it cannot be defined by them. The striker debate rages on, but the protagonists involved ensure that the real winners are those watching from the sidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
